"Hormesis from Low-Dose Radiation"
Hormesis was first
shown to extend life
more than a century ago
when low doses of radiation
were shown to increase
the lifespan
of a type of beetle.
Scientists were hoping
irradiation with x-rays
could kill off the eggs
of the grain pest,
but to their surprise,
at low doses,
it actually made the beetles
live longer.
This was subsequently
replicated with gamma rays,
and in about
a dozen other insects
from house flies and crickets
to wasps and mosquitoes:
a strongly consistent 20 to 60
percent increase in lifespan.
What is going on?
Hormesis is thought to be
an adaptive response
to anticipated
potential threats.
The body is able
to leverage the initial insult
to prompt a compensatory
counter response
that more than covers
the cost of the original damage
and yields a net benefit
in the end.
In the case of radiation,
at high enough doses,
it kills by damaging DNA.
Animals have a whole
DNA repair apparatus,
but it's presumably
too metabolically costly
to have it run at full tilt
all the time
even when
we don't really need it.
But ramping up DNA insults
with low dose radiation
signals to the animal
that they are in a DNA
destructive environment;
so, their body starts ramping up
DNA repair to compensate.
And a happy side effect of
all that extra DNA protection
is a longer life.
That which didn't kill them
made them stronger.
Hormesis is not just
for insects.
It may explain
the findings of the study
"Low-dose radiation
from A-bombs
elongated lifespan
and reduced cancer mortality
relative to un-irradiated
individuals."
The atomic bombs dropped
on Hiroshima and Nagasaki
killed approximately
200,000 people instantaneously,
and survivors exposed
to high levels of radiation
suffered from high rates
of cancer and shortened lives.
However, those exposed
to lower levels of radiation
living farther
from the blast site
appeared to end up
with lower cancer mortality
and longer average lifespans.
Exceptional medical services
provided to
the surviving victims
under the Law Concerning Relief
to Atomic Bomb Survivors
may explain some
of the longevity benefit,
but it also could have been
a hormetic effect.
"Nothing in life
is to be feared,"
Madame Curie,
who won the Nobel Prize
for discovering radioactivity,
is quoted as saying,
"it is only to be understood."
Of course,
this is coming from a woman
who died of bone marrow failure
from radiation exposure,
such that her remains were
interred in a lead-lined coffin.
Why would animals evolve to be
able to withstand radiation?
Because we're bombarded
day and night
by cosmic rays
from the universe.
Our bodies are exposed to
about 20,000 hits of radiation
every second.
But what if we weren't?
Scientists have found
that single-celled organisms
like paramecia
don't grow as well
in lead boxes,
and the thicker the lead walls,
the more their growth
is stunted.
Human cells grown under
similarly shielded conditions
show an increase in levels
of DNA damage and mutations.
This suggests the natural
background radiation
of the Earth
has the hormetic benefit
of keeping our body on its toes.
Even a foot (0.3048 m) of lead
only blocks about
a third of cosmic rays.
To really see
what life would be like
without constant bombardment,
scientists descended
more than a mile (1.6 km)
down into the Earth
into SNOLAB,
the Sudbury Neutrino
Observatory,
set at the bottom
of a nickel mine in Canada.
Contrary to expectations,
fish raised deep underground
grew bigger and heavier
than those raised
on the surface.
The researchers suggested the
silencing of cosmic radiation
may have been offset
by increased radiation
from radon gas
trapped in the mine.
Bottom line: we don't know
enough about low-level radiation
to exploit any hormetic effects
without potentially being
exposed to unacceptable risks.
Thankfully, there are salutary
ways to harness hormesis
for health and longevity.